Robert A. W. Lowndes Papers
Robert A. W. Lowndes Papers
1923-1996
Lowndes, Robert W.
2.75 linear ft.
Correspondence, printed material and memorabilia of the American science fiction author, editor and fan.
2746169
Biographical History
Robert Augustine Ward "Doc" Lowndes (1916-1998), also known by the nicknames "Rawl," was an American science fiction and horror author, editor and fan. He was a notable member of the Futurians, a group influential in the development and recognition of science fiction, and received the First Fandom Hall of Fame award in 1991.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Robert A. W. Lowndes Papers consists of biographical material, correspondence, financial material, memorabilia, printed material and writings.
Biographical material consists of the Spring 2000 issue of Fantasy Commentator; published shortly after Lowndes' death, it contains numerous tributes to Lowndes by science fiction authors and colleagues, as well as one of Lowndes' poems.
Correspondence spans nearly forty years and includes both incoming and outgoing letters. Represented are some of the best-known names in science fiction, including Isaac Asimov, John Brunner, Lin Carter, Stanton Coblentz, L. Sprague de Camp, Lester del Rey, Damon Knight, Frederik Pohl, Donald Wollheim and others. Also present is correspondence with Lowndes' agent Virginia Kiddl; a few from noted Neopagan Leo Martello, and a copious (though short-lived) correspondence with astrologer Jerryl Keane.
Financial material consist of a few years of tax information.
Memorabilia includes Lowndes' baptism and confirmation records, a genealogy of the Lowndes family, a horoscope prepared for Lowndes by Jerryl Keane, report cards, and a scrapbook of Walt Kelly's Pogo cartoons.
Printed material consists of issues of various publications, for some of which Lowndes was the editor. Most relate to science fiction but there are also submissions and issues of The Scandal Sheet, a zine published by the Scandalous Bohemians of New Jersey who appear to have been a Sherlock Holmes fan club.
Writings includes typescripts, carbons, notes and other material relating to articles, books, short stories, zines and other assorted genres. Of particular interest is the relatively complete draft of a book on Hugo Gernsback and typescripts of two of Lowndes' novels. The miscellaneous material includes a summary of a sermon and the rules for a game called "Seven Seas" based around the idea of insurance for ships on the high seas.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondence; material within each folder is arranged chronologically with the exception of the miscellaneous letter files, which are arranged A-Z by surname, and the unidentified items, which are arranged A-Z by first name. Writings are subdivided by type and then alphabetical by title. All other series are arranged alphabetically by type or title.
Related Material
has the papers of a numner of important authors, editors and publishers of early science fiction, including Mercury Press, Spiral Press, Street and Smith, Hugo Gernsback, Forrest Ackerman, and more. For a complete listing, please refer to our.
Subject and Genre Headings
Science fiction; Ashley, Michael.; Asimov, Isaac, 1920-1992.; Bergeron, Richard.; Blish, James.; Coblentz, Stanton A. (Stanton Arthur), 1896-1982.; De Camp, L. Sprague (Lyon Sprague), 1907-2000.; Del Rey, Lester, 1915-1993.; Dziemianowicz, Stefan R.; Geis, Richard.; Gernsback, Hugo, 1884-1967.; Keane, Jerryl L.; Knight, Damon, 1922-2002.; Lowndes, Robert W.; Martello, Leo Louis.; Moskovitz, Sam.; Payes, Rachel Cosgrove.; Pohl, Frederik.; Searles, A. Langley.; Weinberg, Robert E.; Wollheim, Donald A.; Believer's worlds.; Fantasy Commentator.; Mystery of the third mine.; Warhoon.; Holmes, Sherlock (Fictitious character) -- Societies, etc.; Science fiction, American.; Science fiction, American -- History and criticism.; Science fiction fans.; Zines.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Essays.; Manuscripts for publication.; Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Zines.; Authors.; Editors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Ruth Lowndes, 2000.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Memorials, 2000; Spring 2000 issue of Fantasy Commentator, with numerous tributes to Lowndes by science fiction authors and colleagues, also includes one of Lowndes' poems (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - —, Spike and Peggy, 1961-1962; includes "Criticism and the community theatre" by Lowndes (Box 1)
  - Abe, Masaki, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Asimov, Isaac, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Ashley, Mike, 1976-1983; 1990-1993; includes draft of Ashley's bibliography of Lowndes (Box 1)
  - A, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Bergeron, Richard, 1961-1964; 1968-1971,; 1980; includes issues of Warhoon and other zines; photostats of letters to Bergeron from other authors, e.g. Larry Pournelle (Box 1)
  - Bowers, Bill, 1974; 1984-1987; includes two short articles by Lowndes (part of a series called "Understandings") and a list of the full series (Box 1)
  - Brunkhurst, Donna and Scott, 1974-1979 (Box 1)
  - Brunner, John, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Budrys, Algis, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Busby, F. M., 1984 (Box 1)
  - B, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - C. S. Lewis Society, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Cannon, Peter Hughes, 1990; 1994 (Box 1)
  - Carr, Terry, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Carter, Lin, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Chauvin, Cy, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Coblentz, Stanton, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Cook, Michael, 1981; includes two articles by Lowndes (Box 1)
  - Cox, Arthur Jean, 1985; includes photocopy of 1967 article by Cox, "If I hide my watch..." (Box 1)
  - C, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Danner, Bill, 1975-1987 (Box 1)
  - de Camp, L. Sprague, 1961-1962; 1975,; 1980; includes reprint of de Camp's "Master Gunner Appollonius" (Box 1)
  - de la Ree, Gerry, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Del Rey, Judy-Lynn, See Del Rey, Lester.
  - Del Rey, Lester, 1967; 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Dziemianowicz, Stefan, 1992; includes typescript of article, "The Horror Pulpit" (Box 1)
  - D, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Elliot, Jeffrey M., 1979-1980; includes transcript of interview with Lowndes, photocopies of photographs (Box 1)
  - Eschbach, Lloyd Arthur, 1983 (Box 2)
  - E, miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Fantasy and Science Fiction Magazine, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Feeley, Gregory, 1983-1986; includes essay on James Blish by Feeley (Box 2)
  - Folsom, Henry T., 1970; includes typescript, "Through the Years at Baker Street: A Sherlock Holmes Chronology" by Folsom (Box 2)
  - Geis, Richard, 1970-1975; 1986,; 1996; includes several issues of "The Geis Letter" and an essay on James Blish by Geis (Box 2)
  - Gould, William (Bill), 1978-1979; 1982 (Box 2)
    See also Writings: Miscellaneous: Historical pageant.
  - G, miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Hoch, Edward D., 1971-1975; 1983 (Box 2)
  - Hubin, Allen, 1971-1972; 1976,; 1979 (Box 2)
  - H, miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - I, miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Jacks, Herman R., 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Keane, Jerryl, 1963-1964; 1983-1987; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Ketterer, David, 1983-1984; 1987; includes two articles by Ketterer on James Blish (Box 3)
    See also Memorabilia: Horoscope.
  - Kidd, Virginia, 1966-1967; 1971-1973,; 1976-1986; Lowndes' agent (Box 3)
  - Knight, Damon, 1975-1977; includes typescript of Knight's short story "Resilience" (Box 3)
  - Kyle, Richard, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Lupoff, Richard, 1973; 1977 (Box 3)
  - L, miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Madle, Robert, 1971; 1977,; 1979-1981; includes "apprecation" piece on Stanton Coblentz by Madle (Box 3)
  - Martello, Leo, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Michel, Johnny, 1960-1963; includes some of Lowndes' poetry (Box 3)
  - Morrow, Dan, See Scandalous Bohemians of New Jersey
  - Moskovitz, Sam, 1967; 1984-1985 (Box 3)
  - Muller, Marya, 1985-1987 (Box 3)
  - M, miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Nevins, Francis, 1969-1971; includes typescript and reprint of Nevins' "The wild and woolly world of Harry Stephen Keeler" (Box 3)
  - New England Science Fiction Association (NESFA), 1972-1973; 1977 (Box 3)
  - N, miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Payes, Rachel Cosgrove, 1971; 1980 (Box 3)
  - Pohl, Frederik, 1969; 1974,; 1978,; 1981,; 1993 (Box 3)
  - Porianda, Alex (Alexei), 1976-1978; 1993,; undated (Box 3)
  - Pugmire, William, 1974-1976 (Box 3)
  - P, miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Quinn, Margaret (Mrs. Seabury Quinn), 1975; undated (Box 3)
  - Ramsey, Shawn, 1987 (Box 3)
  - R, miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Scandalous Bohemians of New Jersey, 1971-1978; 1993; see also Printed material: Scandal Sheet (Box 3)
  - Searles, A. Langley, 1986; 1993; includes two issues of Fantasy Commentator with a note from Searles to Lowndes (Box 3)
  - Slawson, Winifred (Winnie), 1985-1987; 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Smith, Curtis, 1979-1980; 1985; St. James (publisher) (Box 4)
  - Spencer, Paul, 1971; 1975,; 1978,; 1984 (Box 4)
  - Stone, Graham, 1987 (Box 4)
  - Stone, Leslie, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - S, miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - T, miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Waller, Gabrielle, 1964-1965; includes detailed critique by Lowndes of unnamed novel by Waller (Box 4)
  - Weinberg, Robert and Phyllis, 1960; 1968-1983,; undated; includes photocopy of article by Will Murray on John Nanovic, "The man who almost edited Astounding" (Box 4)
  - Wellman, Manly Wade, 1960 (Box 4)
  - Wollheim, Donald, 1987 (Box 4)
  - W, miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Unidentified, A-Z by first name (Box 4)
- Financial material
  - Taxes, 1977-1979 (Box 4)
- Memorabilia
  - Confirmation and baptism, 1956-1957 (Box 4)
  - Genealogy of the Lowndes family, undated (Box 4)
  - Horoscope, 1965; "for Rawl on his 1965 birthday with affection and best wishes from Jupiter, Nefertiti, Bouncing Besty, Funny Face, and Jerryl" (Box 4)
  - School days, 1923-1933; grade cards; diploma and class photo from Darien High School, Darien, Connecticut (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook of "Pogo" cartoons, undated; newspaper clippings of Walt Kelly's "Pogo" cartoon (Box 4)
- Printed material
  - Fantasy Commentator - see, See Correspondence: Searles, Langley; Biographical material: Memorials
  - Renascence, volumes 1 and 2, 1945-1946 (Box 4)
  - The Scandal Sheet, volumes 1 and 2, 1971-1976 (Box 4)
  - The Scandal Sheet submissions, 1971-1976; assorted articles, essays, puzzles, etc. submitted to the zine, many be Dan Morrow; some have notes or letters attached (Box 4)
  - Warhoon, See Correspondence: Bergeron, Richard.
  - Miscellaneous clippings, 1965; 1979,; undated; originals and photocopies, includes several by Arnold Lieberman, M.D. (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1944; 1971; issue of "True Confessions," issue of "Luna Monthly" with cover piece on August Derleth (Box 4)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Aufgeknopft, undated; typescript carbon with corrections (Box 5)
    - Criticism and the community theater - see, See Correspondence: —, Spike and Peggy.
    - Damon Knight, 1978; galleys of column about Knight, written for Noreascon (Box 5)
    - G. K. Chesterton's Father Brown, undated; photocopy of 1970 printing with corrections (Box 5)
    - The horror out of print, undated; typescript photocopy (Box 5)
    - Hugo Gernsback: A man with a vision, undated; photocopy of galleys (Box 5)
    - Profile of Detective Science Monthly, See Correspondence: Cook, Michael.
    - Profile of Weird Terror Tales, See Correspondence: Cook, Michael.
    - Scientific Detective Monthly, undated (Box 5)
    - Understandings [series of articles], See Correspondence: Bowers, Bill.
    - Weird fiction, horror fiction -- what's the difference?, undated (Box 5)
    - You know my methods, Watson, undated (Box 5)
    - [untitled, on horror], undated; missing page 1 (Box 5)
  - Books
    - Believer's Worlds, typescript carbon, with corrections (Box 5)
    - Mystery of the Third Mine, typescript carbon, with corrections; original title appears to have been "Bonanza in the Sky"; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Hugo Gernsback, Prophet of Science, typescripts (multiple of each chapter), some with corrections, plus research material; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - The Puzzle Planet, typescript carbon, minor corrections (Box 6)
  - Stories
    - Immortal Sleuths, drafts, notes (Box 6)
    - [short story collection], 1970; includes letter to Forrest Ackerman (Box 6)
  - Zines
    See also Printed material: Renascence; Printed material: The Scandal Sheet, for both of which Lowndes was editor.
    - Afterthoughts, issue #1 (Box 6)
    - Agenbite of Inwit, 1945-1949; no actual issues, but correspondence with S. I. Hayakawa, Hayden Carruth, Jules Kolodny, and other regarding permission to reprint articles; also copyright certificates (Box 6)
    - New Annals of Arkya, 1944-1945; 1944 issue is a photocopy, 1945 issue is original (Box 6)
    - Venal, 1946; issue #1 and #2 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Catechism for "A matter of faith", undated; background notes on the religions of the world of Ein (Box 6)
    - Historical pageant (with William Gould), 1960 (Box 6)
    - Index to James Blish's contributions to the mailings of the Vanguard Amateur Press Association, 1979; also includes research material (copies of some articles by Blish an a clipping about him) (Box 6)
    - Sermon summary, 1969; summary of a sermon by Rev. Leland Stark and a letter from Stark complimenting him on it (Box 6)
    - Seven Seas, undated; outline of and rules for a game (Box 6)
    - Fragments, undated (Box 6)
    - Author undetermined, undated; three items, author unknown (Box 6)